<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached to the gentlemen of Yorkshire at Bow-Church in London, the 24th of June, 1684, being the day of their yearly feast by Tho. Cartwright ...</title>
            <author>Cartwright, Thomas, 1634-1689.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1684</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 84 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 22 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A35080</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C705</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R4837</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13682538</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13682538</idno>
            <idno type="VID">101319</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A35080)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 101319)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 841:21)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached to the gentlemen of Yorkshire at Bow-Church in London, the 24th of June, 1684, being the day of their yearly feast by Tho. Cartwright ...</title>
                  <author>Cartwright, Thomas, 1634-1689.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 38 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Tho. Flesher ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1684.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Proverbs XXIV, 21-22 --  Sermons.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Monica Tsuneishi</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Monica Tsuneishi</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:101319:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preached to the GENTLEMEN OF YORKSHIRE, At <hi>Bow-Church</hi> in <hi>LONDON,</hi> The 24th of <hi>June,</hi> 1684.</p>
            <p>Being the Day of their Yearly FEAST.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Tho. Cartwright</hi> D. D. Dean of <hi>Ripon,</hi> and Chaplain in Ordinary to His MAJESTY.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Tho. Fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſher,</hi> at the Angel and Crown in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard. 1684.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:101319:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:101319:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>To all my very much <hi>Honoured Friends,</hi> the <hi>reſpective Natives</hi> of the County of YORK; more eſpecially to thoſe of the <hi>Late Solemn Meeting,</hi> and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly to the <hi>Worthy Stewards</hi> of the FEAST,
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Sir</hi> Robert Legard,</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Sir</hi> Thomas Yarburgh,</item>
                  <item>Abſtrupas Danby,</item>
                  <item>Richard Thornton,</item>
                  <item>Lionel Richardſon,</item>
                  <item>Chriſtopher Todd,</item>
                  <item>George Sayer,</item>
                  <item>John Hatfield,</item>
                  <item>Henry Rapier,</item>
                  <item>David Prole,</item>
                  <item>George Talbott,</item>
                  <item>William Wyler.</item>
               </list>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIRS,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IN an Age wherein <hi>Religion and Loyalty</hi> have been of late ſo much <hi>out of faſhion,</hi> I could not but be very well pleaſed to find ſuch a <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe</hi> as this, ſo <hi>acceptable</hi> to a conſiderable part of the <hi>greateſt County</hi> in the Kingdom, as that <hi>You</hi> not only gave it the <hi>hearing,</hi> (though I tryed your patience, more than would have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come me upon any other Subject than <hi>The Whole
<pb facs="tcp:101319:3"/> Duty of Man)</hi> but were alſo pleas'd <hi>una imouſly to command</hi> the <hi>Publication</hi> of it for the benefit of others who might need the counſel of my Text, more than your ſelves. How <hi>unfit I was</hi> to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form the Task which you laid upon me, my own Reaſon (though exceeding weak) does ſufficiently reſolve me; but the <hi>Subject</hi> is ſuch as will recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend it ſelf, and the <hi>weaker my Diſcourſe</hi> upon it is, the <hi>more pregnant Teſtimony</hi> will it be of my <hi>Obſequiouſneſs</hi> to your Commands, when I ſhall have <hi>given up it and my Underſtanding</hi> to your Pleaſure If it help to make any <hi>better Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians</hi> or <hi>Subjects,</hi> I ſhall think <hi>my Pains</hi> very well <hi>beſtowed,</hi> and be very thankful for the Honour you have done me in laying <hi>your Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands</hi> upon me to <hi>undertake</hi> this Imployment, and giving me this fair <hi>opportunity</hi> of teſtifying to the World, how ready I am to approve my ſelf,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your moſt faithful and obedient Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant in all Offices of true Piety and Loyalty, THO. CARTWRIGHT.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:101319:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>PROV. 24. 21, 22.</bibl>
               <q>My Son, Fear thou the Lord and the King, and meddle not with them that are given to change: For their Cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity ſhall riſe ſuddenly, and who know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the ruine of them both?</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Author of this <hi>Advice to a Son,</hi> was <hi>Solomon,</hi> the <hi>wiſeſt</hi> of Men by the Teſtimony of <hi>Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Ki<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g. 3. 12.</note> 
               <hi>it ſelf;</hi> and of all his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine <hi>Proverbs</hi> or <hi>Aphoriſms,</hi> this of my Text is the choiceſt, being a ſhort and ſelect ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, which he requires his Son to get by heart, and recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends to his practice as the greateſt piece of Piety and Policy he could teach him. 'Tis indeed the <hi>Whole
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:101319:4"/> Duty of Man,</hi> which <hi>Solomon</hi> here preaches and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhes (not in his <hi>own Name,</hi> and as ſome would have it <hi>in favour of himſelf</hi> as a King, but) in the Name of the <hi>God of Wiſdom,</hi> whoſe Image and Superſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion it bears; 'tis the Language of the Holy Scriptures, and hath the Breathings of the <hi>Spirit of God</hi> upon it, by whom he was inſpired to give this <hi>Divine Counſel,</hi> not only to <hi>Rehoboam</hi> the Prince, as his Natural Son; nor to his <hi>own Subjects</hi> only of <hi>Judah</hi> and <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> as his Politick Sons; but as a <hi>Divine Prophet,</hi> to <hi>us</hi> alſo, <hi>upon whom the ends of the World are come,</hi> as his <hi>Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Sons;</hi> to all ſorts and degrees of Men, but eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially to them, who would be thought not <hi>to live with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out God in the World, nor to be Aliens to the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth of Iſrael, or Strangers to the Covenant of Grace,</hi> but to be the Legitimate <hi>Sons of God and Solomon;</hi> 'tis to them that he directs his <hi>Paternal Counſel,</hi> whom he calls <hi>his Sons,</hi> to ſhew his <hi>love</hi> to them, as well as his <hi>power</hi> over them: And to ſatisfie them that their <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Precept</hi> will be for his <hi>Sons Profit,</hi> he bids them look upon <hi>Obedience</hi> to God and the King, not as any <hi>ſervile Yoak</hi> put upon their <hi>Natural Liberty,</hi> which they might watch a <hi>fair opportunity</hi> to ſhake off when they could, but to pay the duty of <hi>Fear to them both,</hi> upon <hi>Filial Principles,</hi> which is the <hi>Glorious Liberty of</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 8. 21.</note> 
               <hi>the Sons of God, wherewith Chriſt hath made us free,</hi> and in which St. <hi>Paul</hi> commands us to <hi>ſtand faſt,</hi> as<note place="margin">Gal. 5. 1.</note> well as <hi>Solomon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which is a more <hi>ſeaſonable Subject</hi> for this Place, and theſe Times, than any <hi>Honeſt</hi> Man could wiſh it, and that on which the <hi>meaneſt Preacher</hi> may ſpeak more with caſe, than ſome of his <hi>Auditors</hi> can hear <hi>with patience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the words of my Text we have,</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:101319:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>I. A <hi>Paternal Precept, My Son, fear thou the Lord and the King;</hi> in which I muſt obſerve,</p>
            <p n="1">1. The <hi>Affection</hi> which he commands his Son to cheriſh in his Breaſt, and that is <hi>fear.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The <hi>Proper Objects</hi> of it, and thoſe in <hi>Solomons</hi> Judgment are <hi>God and the King,</hi> in which give me leave to obſerve two things;</p>
            <p n="1">1. The <hi>Methodical Order</hi> and diſpoſition of the words, <hi>Firſt God,</hi> and then the <hi>King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The <hi>cloſe and intimate connexion</hi> between <hi>God and the King,</hi> 'tis the neareſt that may be, for there is no disjunctive, but a meer copulative between them, they are joyn'd together by that <hi>Wiſdom which is from above;</hi> even by the <hi>Spirit of Wiſdom,</hi> and none but a <hi>Man of Belial</hi> will ever attempt to put them aſunder.</p>
            <p>II. A <hi>Peremptory Prohibition,</hi> Meddle not <hi>with them that are given to change;</hi> not with <hi>Tale-bearers,</hi> who do falſly accuſe others to the King, nor with them who <hi>ſpeak evil of him</hi> and his Government to the People.</p>
            <p>III. The <hi>Proper Suggeſtion</hi> upon which that <hi>Prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition</hi> is grounded, or the <hi>reaſon of that reſtraint,</hi> which he lays upon his Son, drawn from the Changers, and the Medlers doom, which is aggravated from Four Particulars.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Its certainty,</hi> doubt it not, their calamity <hi>ſhall riſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Its ſuddenneſs,</hi> it ſhall ſurpriſe them <hi>ſuddenly</hi> and unexpectedly.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Its ſtrangeneſs,</hi> 'tis a <hi>Nemo ſcit,</hi> who knows it?</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Its extent,</hi> it will reach to the <hi>ruine</hi> both of the <hi>Changers and Medlers,</hi> for they ſhall be both ruin'd, and receive to themſelves Damnation both Temporal and Eternal.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:101319:5"/>
            <p>I know you want a <hi>Remembrancer</hi> more than an <hi>Instructor</hi> in this <hi>Leſſon of Piety and Loyalty;</hi> give me leave therefore to <hi>ſtir up that knowledge which is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready in you,</hi> that ſo you may go away the <hi>more conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate,</hi> if not the more <hi>intelligent</hi> from this Exerciſe; and to ſay with St. <hi>Peter</hi> in the like caſe, <hi>I will not be negligent to put you in remembrance of theſe things,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Pet. 1. 12, 13.</note> 
               <hi>though ye know them and be eſtabliſh'd in the preſent truth, yea I think it meet to ſtir you up by putting you in remembrance,</hi> of</p>
            <p>1. <hi>The Paternal Precept,</hi> My Son, Fear thou the Lord and the King. Now</p>
            <p>1. <hi>The affection,</hi> which he commands his Son to cheriſh in his heart is <hi>fear;</hi> and there is <hi>no paſſion</hi> more <hi>neceſſary</hi> for all ſorts of Men than this of <hi>fear,</hi> the early want whereof was ſo <hi>viſible in our firſt Parents;</hi> for had they fear'd, they had not fell, but this their Guardian Angel being departed from them, they quickly loſt their Innocence and Paradiſe. The <hi>only care</hi> muſt be, that it be plac'd upon <hi>its right ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects,</hi> and theſe in <hi>Solomons Judgment</hi> are only two, God and the King.</p>
            <p n="1">1. He counſels us to fear God with a Filial Fear of Reverence and Circumſpection, a <hi>Conſciencious Fear</hi> in Worſhipping him, and a <hi>Careful Fear</hi> of offend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him, ſuch as becomes all ingenuous and duti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Children, who out of love to their Parents are afraid of diſpleaſing them, and of falling ſhort of their duty to them; which Filial Fear, he who is <hi>born of God,</hi> cannot put off, but he will be fearful of <hi>any ſtone of ſtumbling</hi> in the whole courſe of his life, which may make him <hi>fall into Sin,</hi> and will make it his princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal care and deſign to approve the <hi>ſincerity</hi> of his heart to the piercing eye of a <hi>jealous God,</hi> which <hi>Fear</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:101319:5" rendition="simple:additions"/> diſcovers it ſelf, not in a <hi>trembling amazement,</hi> but in a <hi>chearful and uniform Obedience</hi> to all his Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; which is ſuch a <hi>divine fear</hi> as never <hi>damps his Spirits,</hi> or <hi>robs him of thoſe ſuccours which Reaſon would afford him,</hi> but makes him <hi>as bold as a Lyon,</hi> and may<note place="margin">Prov. 28. 1.</note> therefore be juſtly termed <hi>the beginning or princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 9. 10.</note> 
               <hi>part of Wiſdom.</hi> And indeed what greater <hi>folly and madneſs</hi> can the moſt deſperate Malefactor be guilty of, than to commit <hi>Capital Crimes</hi> in the ſight of his Judge? And yet <hi>how eaſily</hi> are we tempted to offend the <hi>dreadful Majeſty of the Omnipreſent and Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty Judge,</hi> who obſerves our cloſeſt Actions, and will infallibly <hi>call us to account</hi> for them, and reward us <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to what we have done in the fleſh, whether it have been good or evil? When you walk in the ways of</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 16. 27. Eccl. 11. 9.</note> 
               <hi>your own hearts, and in the ſight of your eyes, remember that for all theſe things God will bring you to Judgment.</hi> And <hi>knowing this terrour of the Lord, let me perſwade</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 5. 11.</note> 
               <hi>you,</hi> not to let your <hi>Lives</hi> give your <hi>Lips</hi> the lye, when you ſay that you <hi>fear him;</hi> but conſider that you na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally fix your eyes upon that which you fear, and cannot eaſily get that out of your minds which doth affright you. If therefore you pretend to be afraid of Gods diſpleaſure, where is your tenderneſs of <hi>his Honour?</hi> Your care to <hi>pleaſe him,</hi> your <hi>zeal</hi> for his Cauſe and Service, your delight in his Commands, and your rejoycing to do his Will? You cannot <hi>fear</hi> his Name, and <hi>blaſpheme</hi> it: If againſt the clear evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of his Word, and your own Conſciences, you entertain any rebellious thoughts againſt the <hi>Lord</hi> whom you ſhould <hi>fear,</hi> you can neither eſcape his ſight in this life, nor his vengeance in the next. Be not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd, <hi>God is not mock'd,</hi> by wearing his Livery, and doing the Devil Service; by talking as if you were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpir'd,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:101319:6"/> and had <hi>Cloven Tongues,</hi> and yet acting as if you were <hi>poſſeſs'd,</hi> as ſome <hi>Cloven Footed Proteſtants</hi> have of late done. There is no way to pleaſe God,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 10. 5. Jam. 1. 22.</note> but by <hi>bringing into captivity every thought to the obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience of Chriſt: Be ye therefore doers of his Word, and not hearers only:</hi> Indent not with him to ſpare you, no not in your darling ſins, but reſiſt them to the blood, becauſe the keeping of ſome of his Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, will not expiate for the breach of the reſt: Make no <hi>League</hi> with any <hi>Gibeonite;</hi> ſpare no <hi>Agag,</hi> no ruling ſin, but <hi>crucifie the Old Man with his affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and luſts;</hi> Daſh all thoſe Babyloniſh Brats againſt the ſtones, which are Traytors to the Crown and Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of the King of Heaven; throw them from you with the ſame indignation that you would do thoſe loathſom things which you cannot behold without great diſtemper: Let Chriſt be your King on Earth, and he will be your Saviour in Heaven: Be as ready to be over-ruled by him here, as to be rewarded by him hereafter; ſo ſhall you prove your ſelves to be <hi>Solomon's Sons</hi> indeed, nay <hi>Sons of God,</hi> and Heirs of Eternal Glory: always provided, that to this <hi>fear of God,</hi> you add that of <hi>the King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>My Son, Fear the King.</hi> God commands us to ſubdue our wills<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to that will of Man on Earth, that he may the better ſubdue us to his own will in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; and accordingly our Saviour came into the World to <hi>take away the Sins,</hi> not the <hi>Laws</hi> of it. Nor was the Religion he eſtabliſhed deſigned to looſe the Reins of Civil Government, but to keep Subjects under the ſame and greater Obligations than he found them; to make <hi>ſacred</hi> the <hi>Perſons</hi> as well as <hi>Offices</hi> of Princes, and to eſtabliſh their <hi>juſt Prerogatives,</hi> as being thoſe <hi>Viſible and Mortal Gods,</hi> whom the Almighty had ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour'd
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:101319:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> with his <hi>Name,</hi> and to whom he had deliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted his Vicegerent power over us, and bound us, <hi>not only for wrath, but alſo for Conſcience ſake, to obey and fear them,</hi> as ordained of him, and to reverence that <hi>Divine Character</hi> of Soveraignty, which that <hi>his Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination</hi> had impreſſed upon them: Fear <hi>Good Kings</hi> as God, <hi>Bad Ones</hi> for him, though they ſhould ſtrain the neceſſary and eſſential Powers of Government be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond its due pitch, and become as very Tyrants, as <hi>Nero</hi> was, whoſe <hi>Power was from God</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s<note place="margin">Rom. 13. 1. 2.</note> judgment, though the <hi>abuſe</hi> of it were from himſelf, and his <hi>way of attaining</hi> it not juſtifiable: For the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Emperors</hi> were not <hi>by right,</hi> but <hi>by force</hi> then Lords of the World, and yet he commands <hi>Every Soul, Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis anima quoniam ex animo,</hi> to be ſincerely <hi>ſubject to them;</hi> and though they were <hi>unworthy</hi> of that <hi>Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity</hi> which they <hi>uſurp'd and abus'd,</hi> yet were they not in any caſe to be <hi>reſiſted under peril of Damnation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Twas <hi>God</hi> made <hi>Solomon King over Iſrael,</hi> not the <hi>Prieſt</hi> or the <hi>People;</hi> and he is ſaid to have <hi>ſet him on</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Chron. 9. 8.</note> 
               <hi>his own Throne,</hi> to let the People know that he did im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately <hi>repreſent his Perſon,</hi> and was <hi>in his ſtead</hi> among them, as his Vicegerent and Lieutenant under him. <hi>Inde eſt Imperator unde &amp; homo antequam Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rator,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tertul.</note> 
               <hi>inde poteſtas illi, unde &amp; Spiritus:</hi> He made him a King, who made him a Man; and from him had he his Scepter, from whom he had his Soul. And this was no <hi>Court-Complement</hi> of <hi>Tertullian</hi>'s, (<q rend="margQuotes">None of thoſe Love-Tricks which were plaid between the King and his People in the Honey-Moon of His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Reſtauration, as the <hi>Plato Redivivus,</hi>
               </q> who is not yet out of love with his Commonwealth Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples ſtyles them) nor did he ſpeak it in <hi>his own Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> but as the <hi>Judgment of the whole Catholick Church,</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:101319:7"/> whoſe Cauſe he was then defending: So that the <hi>King</hi> does not Reign it ſeems in the Judgment of the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Church, either by the <hi>Commiſſion of the Pope,</hi> or the <hi>Courteſie of the People,</hi> who can no more <hi>chuſe their Princes,</hi> than <hi>their Parents;</hi> and have as much Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and Religion on their ſide to renounce the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the <hi>one,</hi> as of the <hi>other;</hi> and if there were <hi>any caſe,</hi> in which it might be lawful for us to caſt off the Yoak of their Authority, <hi>who ſhould be judge</hi> of the Fact? Neither the <hi>King</hi> nor <hi>his Subjects,</hi> for both are <hi>Parties:</hi> but <hi>Polybius</hi> his <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the <hi>Law of Hands,</hi> the longeſt Sword muſt be the Arbiter of that Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie; and how bloody a ſentence that will give, on which ſide ſoever it light, our Civil Wars, and the fatal period of them, may eaſily convince us; by which all that we gain'd at laſt, was an endleſs liberty of ruining one another without hope of redreſs. Though the King ſhould oppoſe Gods expreſs and immediate Will, and overturn the very Foundations of Religion, yet the Almighty is able to defend his own Cauſe; nor will He allow <hi>the People,</hi> whoſe Paſſions, Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours and Inſolencies make them always unfit to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come <hi>Reformers,</hi> without and <hi>againſt his expreſs war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant</hi> to uſurp ſo great a Power, as to pretend to any right to reſtrain the Royal Power which they never gave.</p>
            <p>Let us therefore as becomes <hi>Solomon's Sons,</hi> pay the Duty of <hi>Subjection</hi> to <hi>whatſoever Prince</hi> God in his over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruling Providence ſhall think fit to ſet over us: for though he were as bad as <hi>Nebuchadnezzar the King of Babylon,</hi> we muſt either <hi>ſerve him, or periſh eternally,</hi> and they <hi>prophecy a lye to you in Gods Name who preach any other Doctrine,</hi> if the Prophet <hi>Jeremiah</hi> ſay true, <hi>Jer.</hi> 27. 10, 15, 16.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:101319:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>With what <hi>Alacrity</hi> then ſhould we ſubject our ſelves to ſuch a <hi>Pious and Gracious King</hi> as our is, who if he be not in as much <hi>reverence with us,</hi> as he is <hi>in esteem with God,</hi> all our pretended <hi>Piety</hi> to the Depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, will never expiate our <hi>Diſloyalty</hi> to his Deputy; which will the better appear, becauſe the Obedience which God commands us to yield the King, is but the payment of an <hi>Old Debt,</hi> which is due by the Fifth Commandment to the Supreme Father of our Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, to him as <hi>next Heir to Adam,</hi> the firſt <hi>Monarch</hi> of the World, in whom the <hi>Supremacy</hi> was as large and <hi>unlimited</hi> as any act of his <hi>Will;</hi> for God <hi>gave him Dominion over the World,</hi> and made him <hi>Sole Proprie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor</hi> of it, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1. 28. And if he had not been ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly <hi>made the Sovereign Lord of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſe</hi> by that <hi>Special Commiſſion</hi> from the High Court of Heaven, yet <hi>all Mankind</hi> being ſprung from his Loyns, were <hi>born in Subjection</hi> to him by the Law of God and Nature, which inveſted him with a <hi>Patriarchal</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troulable Power,</hi> not only over <hi>his Children,</hi> but alſo over thoſe who were <hi>deſcended from them,</hi> during his life; which being tranſmitted after his death to his <hi>Eldeſt Son and Succeſſor Seth, (Cain</hi> having forfeited his Birth-right by the Murder of <hi>Abel</hi>) and ſo down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards in the right line, there could never be a time till the Flood when the World was not under ſuch a Monarchical Government.</p>
            <p>Now when the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Deluge</hi> had ſwept away all Mankind but <hi>Noah and his Sons; Noah</hi> was not<note place="margin">Gen. 9. 2.</note> 
               <hi>Tenant in common</hi> with his Sons, as <hi>one Lawyers Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion</hi> is, (who was no <hi>better a Friend</hi> to the <hi>Crown</hi> than the <hi>Church</hi>) for God would never have <hi>diſinherited</hi> ſo <hi>juſt and pious a Prince</hi> as <hi>Noah,</hi> whom he made the <hi>Reſtorer of all Mankind:</hi> And therefore <hi>Cedrenus</hi> and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:101319:8"/> 
               <hi>Euſebius</hi> tells us, (as that <hi>Antiquary</hi> knew well enough) that he by the Right which God and Nature had in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſted him with, did Twenty Years before his death make a Partition of the World among his Sons, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lotting to every one his ſhare, which he confirmed by his laſt Will, and gave it into the Hands of <hi>Sem;</hi> and to him over and above his ſhare, after his death, a kind of Supremacy, as Lord in chief over the whole, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſhing them to live peaceably, and not to invade each others Territories.</p>
            <p>Nor did the Kings loſe their Ground, till after <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhuah's time;</hi> for then the <hi>tame People</hi> thought this <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative Doctrine,</hi> which we now Preach, to be whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom Divinity, and yet they were neither <hi>Evil Counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lors,</hi> nor <hi>Flattering Courtiers,</hi> nor <hi>Time-ſerving Prieſts</hi> who put him upon it; nor was he himſelf thought a Tyrant for accepting ſuch an <hi>Arbitrary Power</hi> over them, as this would ſeem to be through a Pair of Modern Spectacles, <hi>Joſh. 1. 10, 11. And they anſwered Joſhua, ſaying, All that thou commandeſt us we will do, and whitherſoever thou ſendeſt us we will go, according as we hearkned to Moſes in all things, ſo will he hearken unto thee; and whoſoever he be that doth rebel againſt thy Commandment in all that thou commandeſt him, he ſhall be put to death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And that the <hi>Kings of England</hi> hold their <hi>Imperial Crowns</hi> (for ſo <hi>Nine ſeveral Statutes</hi> at leaſt do call them) <hi>by the Law of God and Nature,</hi> ſubject to none but the Almighty and <hi>only Ruler of Princes,</hi> and not by <hi>Human Inſtitution,</hi> hath been the agreement of all Parliaments, though of <hi>different Intereſt, Religion and Tempers,</hi> whom they therefore ſtyl'd their <hi>Supreme Natural Liege Lord, Omnes ſub eo &amp; ipſe ſub nullo niſi tantum ſub Deo,</hi> ſaith <hi>Bracton,</hi> who was <hi>Lord Chief Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:101319:8" rendition="simple:additions"/> in</hi> Henry <hi>the Third's time,</hi> next under God, and inferiour to none but him; ſo that his is <hi>Poteſtas Dei Vicaria,</hi> a Ray of Gods Majeſty, who hath arm'd him with the <hi>Power of Life and Death</hi> by his <hi>Commiſſion,</hi> who alone could <hi>put the Sword into his hands</hi> for that purpoſe, as being the <hi>ſole Arbiter of Life and Death,</hi> who only can <hi>take it away,</hi> becauſe <hi>he gave it.</hi> For 'tis plain to all who underſtand any thing but Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion, that the <hi>Peoples Conſent</hi> could not do it, for they have <hi>not Power over their own Lives,</hi> and ſo could not transfer that to another which they had not them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. <hi>His Title</hi> may well be <hi>Dei Gratia,</hi> for <hi>of God</hi> does he hold his Crown <hi>in Capite;</hi> 'tis <hi>by his Grace</hi> that Kings are what they are, and our <hi>Kings of England</hi> have their Crowns unqueſtionably eſtabliſhed by an <hi>Inherent and Independent Right Antecedent</hi> to their <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronations,</hi> by <hi>Birth-right,</hi> by <hi>Conſent,</hi> by <hi>Preſcription,</hi> and <hi>by Law,</hi> which are all the ways whereby <hi>any Right</hi> can be legally eſtabliſhed; and 'tis the <hi>Power of God</hi> in their Hands to which we are required to <hi>ſubject our ſelves;</hi> and the violation of every <hi>particular Law</hi> made by them, does neceſſarily draw along with it the vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of the <hi>general Law of God,</hi> by which he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands<note place="margin">Matth. 22. 21.</note> Obedience to them, <hi>not with eye-ſervice as men-pleaſers, but in ſingleneſs of heart fearing God and the King.</hi> In which words we are diligently to obſerve two things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Their <hi>Methodical Order and Diſpoſition,</hi> Fear them <hi>both</hi> in their <hi>proper Order,</hi> but <hi>Firſt God;</hi> and 'tis<note place="margin">1 Tim. 6. 15.</note> good reaſon, for <hi>He is King of Kings; and Lord of Lords.</hi> If the <hi>King bids,</hi> what <hi>God forbids,</hi> and ſo the <hi>fear</hi> of <hi>both become incompatible,</hi> you muſt <hi>obey God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ather than Man,</hi> becauſe the <hi>Subordinate</hi> muſt <hi>yield</hi> to the <hi>Supreme,</hi> Gods Miniſter to the Maſter and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:101319:9"/> of us all; and therefore though it may be ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times neceſſary <hi>not to obey the King actively,</hi> (as it hapned to the <hi>Captive Jews</hi> under <hi>Nebuchadnezzar,</hi> and to ſome of the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> under the Roman Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors,) for they could not obey God and the King too, and then the <hi>Caſe of Conſcience</hi> was eaſily reſolv'd, in as much as <hi>his Commands</hi> were <hi>countermanded</hi> by an higher and greater Power, and the Obligation of ſuch irregular Precepts reſcinded by a more <hi>indiſputable Authority,</hi> and a more <hi>indiſputable Law</hi> than his, even by the clear <hi>expreſs word of God,</hi> which is the <hi>Stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dard of Obedience</hi> both to him and the King; and yet even then a <hi>paſſive Obedience</hi> was and is neceſſary in the Judgment of the <hi>firſt and beſt Chriſtians,</hi> who when they could <hi>not obey with Piety,</hi> did <hi>dye with Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience,</hi> and lay quietly down under the burden which they durſt not bear; they patiently expected a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs of ſuch unuſual Emergencies from the good Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence of God, for whoſe ſake they ſuffer'd them.</p>
            <p>But alas! In our <hi>Iron-Age</hi> a <hi>little Loyalty</hi> and <hi>leſs Religion</hi> ſerves moſt Mens turns; there is nothing more pretended to, nor any thing leſs practis'd than either; and they who are moſt forward to diſpute <hi>who is</hi> to be fear'd <hi>God or the King, firſt or moſt,</hi> are uſually the Men who (for all their <hi>tender Conſciences,</hi> which ſerve for nothing but to miſcheif others and themſelves) ſeldom <hi>fear</hi> or <hi>obey either;</hi> for if they did, they would obſerve, a little better than they do,</p>
            <p n="2">2ly, The <hi>cloſe Connexion between God and the King,</hi> 'tis ſo near that there is no <hi>Disjunctive,</hi> but a meer <hi>Copulative</hi> between them; <hi>My Son, fear thou God and the King,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and be diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent<note place="margin">Sept.</note> or contumacious to neither of them. If there
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:101319:9" rendition="simple:additions"/> were not a <hi>God in Heaven,</hi> there would be <hi>no Gods on Earth;</hi> nor would <hi>Mankind</hi> ſubject themſelves to <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment,</hi> but that there is ſomething of the <hi>Image of God in it,</hi> to which they are bound by an <hi>Inherent Principle</hi> which <hi>Religion</hi> improves to pay a <hi>Natural Homage.</hi> Our <hi>Civil Peace</hi> would ſoon be turn'd into a <hi>Civil War,</hi> if it were not for this; and therefore there never was any Nation ſo <hi>Impolitick</hi> and <hi>Brui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſhly Barbarous,</hi> but that they embrac'd and eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh'd <hi>ſome Religion</hi> or other among them, as know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing how <hi>great Influence</hi> it had on the Body Politick. <hi>Religion</hi> when <hi>pure and undefil'd,</hi> hath always prov'd a <hi>good Friend to Government;</hi> and that Religion will at laſt be found to be <hi>beſt,</hi> which befriends and <hi>ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens it moſt;</hi> and the <hi>better Chriſtians</hi> Men are, the <hi>better Subjects</hi> they will be: for the Integrity of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Loyalty, as <hi>Arnobius</hi> proves againſt the Gentiles, is greater than that of any <hi>other Religion</hi> which was ever received in the World. <hi>Vos Conſcios timetis, nos Conſcientiam:</hi> You are ſubject for fear your Diſloy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty ſhould riſe up in Judgment againſt you before Men, but we for fear our Conſciences ſhould accuſe us before God. 'Tis the <hi>fear of him</hi> which begets in us the <hi>fear of the King,</hi> who repreſents him, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſes his Authority over us. Our Religion allows not the leaſt oppoſition to be made by any <hi>private Man,</hi> or <hi>any Body of Men</hi> to their Superiours, but ſtrictly and indiſponſibly requires our Subjection to the Authority of the <hi>Worſt Princes,</hi> and forbids our laying violent hands on them, though they were <hi>Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants,</hi> and Invaders of the Peoples Liberties; the very <hi>Worſt of Men</hi> as well as <hi>Kings,</hi> looks not upon their <hi>failings</hi> to be any <hi>abatement of their Power,</hi> nor admits any <hi>Aſylum</hi> for their <hi>Aſſaſſinates</hi> or Murderers. And
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:101319:10"/> I may venture to ſay in all places without the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard of a Quarrel, That the <hi>Principles of the Church of England</hi> are as innocent and peaceable, and at leaſt as <hi>Auxiliary to the Civil Government,</hi> as the <hi>Maxims and Articles</hi> of any Church under Heaven, and much more than thoſe of the <hi>Church of Rome</hi> or <hi>Geneva,</hi> in reſpect of their extravagant <hi>Papal</hi> or <hi>Popular Power,</hi> of the <hi>Conclave</hi> or <hi>Synod,</hi> directly or indirectly exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis'd by either of them <hi>in Ordine ad Spiritualia,</hi> and the <hi>Exemption of their Clergy</hi> from the Coercive Power of Princes. Our Principles are, and have in all Ages been <hi>truly ſerviceable</hi> to the Government of <hi>Civil</hi> as well as of <hi>Religious Societies;</hi> and our Proteſtant Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion eſtabliſh'd by Law, hath <hi>the promiſe of this life and that which is to come,</hi> and may juſtly be term'd <hi>the beſt Reaſon of State:</hi> Nor can any thing be of greater importance to the <hi>Security</hi> or <hi>Ruine of the Kingdom,</hi> than the <hi>well</hi> or <hi>ill Adminiſtration</hi> of it. Moſt certain it is, that no Society can be upheld without <hi>Oaths, Promiſes</hi> and <hi>Engagements,</hi> which are the <hi>Highest Secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity</hi> of which Mankind is capable; nor can any of them hold, unleſs <hi>Religion bind us to it;</hi> and therefore in <hi>Machiavel's Judgment,</hi> (who was none of the beſt Friends to it) 'tis <hi>of great Importance to a State to preſerve a worthy eſteem of it.</hi> And wiſe Princes will both in point of <hi>Gratitude</hi> and <hi>Intereſt</hi> cheriſh the <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Religion,</hi> which is a <hi>part of the Government,</hi> and being <hi>bred up with it,</hi> will be ſure never to give it any diſturbance, by prohibiting and reſtraining <hi>all ſtrange and new Religions,</hi> which will only ſerve to <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe the Kings patience,</hi> and keep him <hi>in breath</hi> with the Diſturbances they will create among his Subjects, (of which the late times have been an unhappy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance) for the prevention whereof, God hath <hi>put the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:101319:10" rendition="simple:additions"/> Sword into his hands,</hi> and he muſt <hi>not bear it in vain,</hi> but <hi>uſe it</hi> whilſt he has it, as a <hi>proper Inſtrument</hi> for the preſervation of <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Piety</hi> in his Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: This is that which makes his <hi>Authority ſo Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign,</hi> and <hi>his Perſon ſo ſacred,</hi> that the Hiſtorian hath placed him <hi>next to God</hi> himſelf, as well as <hi>Solomon, Proximus Diis habetur, per quem Deorum Majeſtas</hi>
               <note place="margin">Juſtin. 1.</note> 
               <hi>vindicatur.</hi> There is but <hi>one fear</hi> in my Text, which is due both <hi>to God and the King;</hi> the Almighty hath <hi>joyn'd them together</hi> as well as <hi>Solomon,</hi> and he would have us do ſo too: therefore neither <hi>the Popes</hi> nor <hi>the Speakers Chair</hi> muſt be ſet <hi>between Gods and the Kings Throne;</hi> no juſt <hi>Interpoſition of any third Perſon and Power,</hi> for our Debt <hi>to God and the King</hi> commences from our <hi>Birth;</hi> and the Duties of <hi>Obedience to God,</hi> and of <hi>Allegiance to the King,</hi> are of the <hi>firſt and great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Importance,</hi> the Obligation whereof muſt be <hi>firſt paid,</hi> or elſe an <hi>Everlaſting Judgment</hi> will be <hi>entred</hi> againſt us in this Life, and infallibly <hi>executed</hi> in the next.</p>
            <p>Now there are <hi>three ſorts of People</hi> who do attempt <hi>to disjoyn God and the King</hi> in this kind; The <hi>Papal Jeſuite,</hi> the <hi>Proteſtant Jeſuite,</hi> and he who pretends to be a <hi>Royaliſt,</hi> and yet diſgraces ſo good a Cauſe by his prophane Life. The two firſt are <hi>Fratres in Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo,</hi> Twins of Rebellion, the Elder is of the <hi>Ignati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Fraternity,</hi> and <hi>Roman Conclave,</hi> who puts the <hi>Pope;</hi> the Younger of the <hi>Puritanical Aſſembly or Claſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis,</hi> which puts <hi>the People between God and the King;</hi> and therefore I call the one <hi>a Papal,</hi> and the other <hi>a Phanatical Jeſuite;</hi> for I believe them both to be <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Penſioners,</hi> two Parties commanded by one Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, becauſe in all times, when the <hi>Government</hi> hath been charging one of them <hi>in the front,</hi> the other hath
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:101319:11"/> always treacherouſly <hi>attack'd it in the rear,</hi> (and as much of late as ever) and both prov'd themſelves in the end, <hi>Abhorrers of Monarchy,</hi> under-hand Contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, and reſtleſs Oppoſers of it, as they always pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend <hi>for Conſcience ſake,</hi> out of a joynt deſign to make the <hi>King a Property,</hi> and his Government Precarious: Their <hi>Names</hi> are <hi>different,</hi> but their <hi>Nature is the ſame</hi> in point of Diſobedience. And the third, <hi>viz.</hi> The <hi>Prophane Liver,</hi> who pretends to Loyalty by making no Conſcience of his Duty towards God, is alſo <hi>a falſe Traytor to the King,</hi> notwithſtanding the many <hi>good words</hi> he gives him, and the great Honour he vainly boaſts in all Companies to bear towards Him.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Give me leave to ſet firſt to the Bar the <hi>Papal Jeſuite,</hi> who is <hi>all for the fear of God,</hi> the Propagation of the <hi>Catholick Religion,</hi> and of the <hi>Apoſtolical See of Rome;</hi> but tell him of the <hi>fear of the King,</hi> and then he leaves you, as if the <hi>Pope</hi> and <hi>He</hi> were the <hi>Real De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders of the Faith,</hi> and the King only the <hi>Nominal and Titular</hi> one; and accordingly he teaches his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>felytes to weigh out their Obedience to him by Drams and Scruples in a Pair of Jeſuitical Scales; makes the <hi>Prince</hi> ſtand to the <hi>Popes Allowance</hi> for Authority, and take<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>his leavings,</hi> who of courſe exempts <hi>all the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy</hi> from their Obedience to their Natural Sovereign, and makes them pay their <hi>Suit and Service</hi> to him as their <hi>Lord Paramount,</hi> as if <hi>his Tribunal</hi> and <hi>Gods</hi> were but one; and the <hi>Civil Magiſtrate</hi> by becoming the <hi>Son of the Church,</hi> had <hi>loſt his Secular Power.</hi> An ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Doctrine to convert Pagan Princes to the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion, or Proteſtants to the Popiſh! The fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal and pernicious Conſequences of which Popiſh Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, our <hi>Parliaments</hi> have in all Ages as well <hi>before
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:101319:11" rendition="simple:additions"/> the Reformation</hi> as <hi>ſince</hi> expreſſed their juſt deteſtation of, as appears by the <hi>Statute of Carliſle,</hi> made 35 <hi>Edw.</hi> 1. and by that <hi>of Proviſo's,</hi> made 25 <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. and by many more in King <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth's Reign, who was both <hi>Parliamentarily</hi> and <hi>Synodically</hi> inveſted with the <hi>Supremacy</hi> in all Cauſes as well Spiritual as Temporal, which was <hi>legally</hi> and <hi>eſſentially inherent</hi> in the Crown before, the King of <hi>England</hi> being <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Ordinary</hi> by the <hi>Antient Common Law</hi> of this Kingdom, of which <hi>thoſe Statutes</hi> were not <hi>Introdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory,</hi> but <hi>Declarative:</hi> And 'tis a great wonder to me, that every Prince in Chriſtendom is not as much poſſeſs'd with an <hi>Anti-Papal Spirit</hi> at this day as ever King <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth was, conſidering what an <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placable Enemy</hi> the <hi>Pope</hi> hath been to the Dignity and Security, to the Powers and Lives of all Princes, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially ſuch as he calls Heretical ones.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The <hi>Proteſtant or Fanatical Jeſuites,</hi> if they would be content to be <hi>civil Subjects,</hi> yet they will be <hi>Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical Superiors;</hi> they would have a King <hi>under</hi> them, not <hi>over</hi> them. The King muſt Command <hi>as they will have him,</hi> or he is <hi>no King for them;</hi> nor will they <hi>fear him,</hi> but make him <hi>fear them,</hi> if they can com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs their ends. He muſt do things <hi>againſt his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, Oath</hi> and <hi>Honour,</hi> againſt the <hi>Fundamental Laws</hi> of the Land, and the <hi>very being</hi> of the Government, or elſe though they ſpeak him as fair as they did his <hi>Roayl Father</hi> of bleſſed memory in the <hi>Covenant,</hi> and ſo hide the <hi>Cloven Foot</hi> for a while with their <hi>broad Phariſaical Phylacteries,</hi> and intrench themſelves in the <hi>ſure retreat</hi> of thoſe popular and plauſible Preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of <hi>preſerving His Majeſties Perſon, and the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Religion,</hi> yet they watch but for a <hi>fair opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity</hi> to put off their <hi>Hypocritical Vizards,</hi> and to make
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:101319:12"/> him feel the <hi>ſmart effects</hi> of their Implacable Enmity againſt him, and let him ſee by woful experience how little they do either <hi>love or fear him,</hi> as they did his Royal Father before him,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>David</hi> was a <hi>Man after Gods own heart,</hi> and had a <hi>Conſcience</hi> truly <hi>tender,</hi> (I would to God all that are call'd ſo in our days were like it) which made him ſo ſenſible of his fault in ſnipping off a ſmall ſhred of the Skirt of <hi>Saul</hi>'s Coat: But our <hi>Diſſenters Itching Fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers</hi> long to be tampering with the <hi>Prerogative,</hi> and will cut off as much as they can get into their hands and throw it to the People, as the <hi>Men of God</hi> did in the late <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Rebellion, (for ſo the deluded Multitude call'd them) though they prov'd <hi>Men of War,</hi> fir'd with <hi>Phanatical Zeal</hi> againſt the <hi>Moſt Chriſtian Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate</hi> in the World, our Martyr'd Sovereign. The <hi>Black Coats</hi> of their Schiſm in ſtead of being <hi>Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers of Peace,</hi> ſounded the Treaſonable Alarms from ſuch places as theſe; though the <hi>Red Coats</hi> fought the Battles, they taught their Congregations to conſtrue the <hi>Singulis Major</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſis Minor</hi> after <hi>Bucha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nan's Tranſlation,</hi> and made them believe, That <hi>the People</hi> (which begins to be as <hi>faſhionable</hi> a word now as it was <hi>Forty years ſince</hi>) <q rend="margQuotes">were as much above the King, as the King is above the meaneſt of his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects. The King (ſay they) and other Magiſtrates are but our Servants to protect us from Violence and<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mene Tekel,</hi> pag. 41.</note> Oppreſſion; and if they break their Truſt, the Law of God and Nature allows us to call our Servants to account, and to puniſh them according to their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merits, and to turn them out of our Service,</q> (<hi>In good time</hi>) and out of the World too, as they did the<note place="margin">Hiſt. of In dep. Part 2. Sect. 80, 81, 82.</note> Royal Martyr, as a Traytor to the Sovereignty of the People, (as that Inſolent Judge <hi>Bradſhaw</hi> then Impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:101319:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſtyl'd it) which corrupt and <hi>falſe Principle</hi> of placing the <hi>Original of Government in our Sovereign Lords the People,</hi> is not only <hi>derogatory to God,</hi> whoſe <hi>Written Word</hi> it gives the <hi>lye</hi> to, but is alſo <hi>deſtructive to the very being of Humane Society:</hi> For if the Power be <hi>radically</hi> in them, and only paſs'd over by the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyance of a <hi>Common Conſent,</hi> with a <hi>Power of Revo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation</hi> upon equitable Conditions <hi>expreſs'd</hi> or <hi>imply'd,</hi> (of which the People ſhall be Judges) it is but <hi>their recalling of that Power,</hi> (to which the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nwary Mobile</hi> may be eaſily tempted, for 'tis <hi>Neutrum modo, mas modo Vulgus</hi>) and the Government is diſſolv'd, and ſo all <hi>our Happineſs</hi> lies <hi>at the Mercy and Will of the Crowd,</hi> which will make us a <hi>reproach to our Neighbours,</hi> and<note place="margin">Pſal. 79. 4.</note> 
               <hi>a ſcorn and deriſion</hi> (as it hath already done in a great meaſure) <hi>to all that are round about us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We live in <hi>an Age</hi> wherein Men ſeem to call them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves <hi>Protestants,</hi> not from that ſolemn and <hi>Honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Proteſtation</hi> which was made by ſeveral Princes againſt the Errours and Superſtitions of <hi>Rome,</hi> and an Edict made in prejudice of the Reformed Religion at <hi>Spires in Germany, A. D.</hi> 1529. but rather from the <hi>Proteſtations</hi> made by the <hi>Covenanting Rebels of Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> againſt Gods and the Kings Authority, <hi>A. D.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hiſt. of I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dep. Part 2. Sect. 100. &amp; 1 1.</note> 1638. and 1639. Firſt againſt the <hi>Function of Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacy</hi> as <hi>Antichriſtian,</hi> and not long after, againſt <hi>the King,</hi> and <hi>Kingſhip it ſelf,</hi> which they firſt <hi>voted down,</hi> and then <hi>abjur'd.</hi> And ſtill their <hi>Impenitent Off-ſpring,</hi> who are Nurs'd up too fondly amongſt us, <hi>fear any thing but God and the King,</hi> being grown ſo over-familiar with both as to contemn them. <hi>Nimia ſuperbia nihil timent:</hi> The Haughty Spirits of our Modern <hi>Seditious Diſſenters,</hi> (the laſt, but worſt Edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Proteſtants, and that which needs much Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:101319:13"/> and Amendment) ſcorn to <hi>ſtoop to Authority,</hi> and therefore they <hi>ſpeak evil of Dignities,</hi> and Libel the Government, and do as much as in them lies to ſcare all the <hi>Princes</hi> in Chriſtendom from <hi>turning Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants,</hi> by reaſon of whom <hi>the Way of Truth,</hi> and of the beſt Religion under Heaven, comes <hi>to be evil ſpoken of,</hi> from whence <hi>our Calamities</hi> do ariſe; and <hi>Solomon</hi> ſays <hi>theirs ſhall ſuddenly ariſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3ly. He who calls himſelf a <hi>Royaliſt,</hi> and yet diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graces ſo <hi>Good a Cauſe</hi> by his <hi>Bad Life,</hi> does alſo <hi>disjoyn God and the King:</hi> He pretends as much to <hi>Honour the King,</hi> as the other two do <hi>to fear God:</hi> He will <hi>Talk, Drink,</hi> and <hi>Fight for him,</hi> but whilſt he makes no Conſcience of his duty to God, but lives in all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Lewdneſs and Prophaneneſs, he is not ſo good a Servant to the King as he would be thought to be; for he does him more hurt by <hi>his Sins,</hi> than he can do him good by <hi>his Sword;</hi> and pulls down more Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments by <hi>his Iniquities,</hi> than he can ever prevent or remove by his <hi>utmost Endeavors:</hi> And therefore though you are ready to <hi>open your Veins and Purſes</hi> for him as becomes you upon all Occaſions, and as your <hi>Loyal Anceſtors of Yorkſhire</hi> did before you for his Father of Bleſſed Memory; yet unleſs you, who have rebell'd againſt him by your evil Lives, do reconcile your ſelves to the King of Heaven, and <hi>make your peace with him,</hi> you are but <hi>Traytors to his Crown and Dignity;</hi> nor can you ever be <hi>truly devoted Servants</hi> to him, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs you are <hi>devout Servants</hi> to the Almighty, <hi>from whom comes his help.</hi> No Man can ſerve his Prince without <hi>Courage</hi> and <hi>Honeſty,</hi> and 'tis the <hi>Fear of God</hi> which is the <hi>right Parent</hi> of both; and therefore as no <hi>true Chriſtian</hi> can ever be a <hi>Rebel,</hi> ſo neither is any <hi>vicious Man</hi> a <hi>truly Loyal Subject,</hi> for how ſervice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:101319:13" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſoever he may be to the King in other Inſtances, the Iniquities which he cheriſhes are ſuch, <hi>for which</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 12. 25.</note> 
               <hi>God will deſtroy both him and the King.</hi> So that all <hi>National Sins</hi> have <hi>High Treaſon</hi> in them; and every <hi>Combination</hi> in ſuch publick Enormities is a <hi>Conſpiracy</hi> and <hi>Rebellion</hi> againſt our King and Country.</p>
            <p>Now as <hi>great Sinners</hi> as the <hi>worſt of you</hi> are, I hope you are all more <hi>Men</hi> than to prove your ſelves <hi>ſuch Beaſts,</hi> as to become <hi>Paracides</hi> to pleaſe a <hi>deſtructive</hi> Luſt, and to imbrue your Hands in your Princes Blood, (to whom you pretend ſo much Duty) rather than <hi>to waſh them in Innocency</hi> for his good and your own. If there be any true <hi>Love and Loyalty</hi> in you to our <hi>Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Sovereign Lord</hi> and his Royal Family; Any Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to your <hi>Native Country;</hi> Any Compaſſion to your <hi>own Souls,</hi> amend your Lives ſpeedily, and do not like <hi>blind Sampſon</hi> pull down the goodly Fabrick of Church and State upon their Heads and your own, by your continued Rebellion againſt Heaven, but live ſo <hi>in the fear of God,</hi> as if you did in earneſt <hi>deſire</hi> and <hi>hope</hi> for better times. Be faithful to the King in your Perſons and Purſes, but let not your <hi>evil Lives</hi> conſpire againſt him. If <hi>our Enmity</hi> againſt the King of Heaven do not <hi>ſhake his Throne,</hi> the <hi>Gates of Hell cannot prevail againſt it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If you <hi>agree</hi> that <hi>God and the King are to be fear'd,</hi> why do you not agree to do it? If either you are <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomons Sons, or Gods Servants;</hi> if your Wiſdom be <hi>from above,</hi> or <hi>of this World,</hi> 'tis more than time that you ſhewed it by putting his <hi>Paternal Precept in pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice,</hi> and taking alſo the <hi>juſt notice</hi> which becomes you of his; <hi>ſecondly Peremptory Prohibition, Meddle not with them that are given to change,</hi> with <hi>Men of Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity and Humour;</hi> for it argues a <hi>great Diſeaſe and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:101319:14"/> Sickneſs</hi> as well in the <hi>Soul</hi> as in the <hi>Body,</hi> whether <hi>Natural, Politick</hi> or <hi>Eccleſiaſtical,</hi> to be continually toſſing from one ſide to the other; Sound Religion, like the Author of it, being <hi>yeſterday, to day, and the ſame for ever;</hi> and that <hi>Form of Government beſt</hi> both in <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State,</hi> into which the <hi>Real Intereſt and Manners</hi> of the People have <hi>run longeſt,</hi> and with the ſtrongeſt Current. Let not <hi>Inconveniences</hi> prevail with you to <hi>break Oaths,</hi> or to <hi>overturn Laws</hi> and <hi>Antient Boundaries,</hi> for nothing hath ſo <hi>great an Inconvenience in it</hi> as that; thoſe are but <hi>partial,</hi> but this would be a <hi>total</hi> one. Now all <hi>Publick Changes</hi> are full of <hi>diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty,</hi> but thoſe in <hi>State</hi> or <hi>Religion</hi> are ſo full of <hi>dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger too,</hi> that it hath always been thought fit, by Wiſe Men, to bear with ſome <hi>tolerable Defects and Evils</hi> in either, rather than by endeavouring to <hi>reform them,</hi> to hazard the <hi>marring of all the reſt.</hi> And though <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt</hi> in ſuch as <hi>deſire a change</hi> do often make them ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend <hi>more Advantages</hi> than really there are, and cover thoſe <hi>very Doubts and Dangers</hi> they are privy to, for fear of diſheartning thoſe <hi>ſhort-ſighted Men</hi> who are unadviſedly <hi>Imbark'd</hi> in their deſigned Innovations; yet the <hi>ſharpeſt eye-ſight</hi> is not able to reach the <hi>ſad Conſequences and fatal End</hi> of ſuch Attempts: For ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>their Counſels</hi> muſt be back'd <hi>with Arms,</hi> or they will prove dangerous to the Undertakers; and ſo they who have ingag'd themſelves and others in ſuch a deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate deſign, are <hi>reduc'd</hi> before they are aware to the <hi>Vicious Neceſſity of more deſperate Remedies,</hi> and do often make choice of thoſe, which are much <hi>more miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chievous</hi> than the <hi>Diſeaſes</hi> which they pretend to cure. There are few Men <hi>Ingag'd in any Faction,</hi> who are <hi>ſo wiſe</hi> as to <hi>ſee their own Miſtakes,</hi> or <hi>ſo ingenuous</hi> as to confeſs them when they ſee them. Beſides, the fear
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:101319:14" rendition="simple:additions"/> and jealouſie of being <hi>call'd to a future account</hi> for the breach of the known Laws of the Kingdom, does na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally beget more rebellious Attempts in thoſe In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croaching Subjects, who being conſcious to themſelves of their having exceeded the limits of Duty and Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to their lawful Sovereign, will do what in them lies, to debaſe the King <hi>below the condition of any free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born Subject,</hi> and by <hi>factious and ſeditious Reflections</hi> on the Government, will keep the <hi>Wounds of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> open, that they may ſuck its <hi>Blood,</hi> and ſave their own, which has been the unwarrantable practice of ſome <hi>Brokers of Sedition</hi> in theſe days, for whom the <hi>Kings Bench</hi> is a much fitter place than the <hi>Royal Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By all which it will appear, that the <hi>Changing of Religion</hi> under any <hi>Comprehenſive Notion</hi> whatſoever, is the moſt <hi>deſperate Paroxyſm</hi> that can happen to a <hi>ſickly State;</hi> and therefore <hi>Maecenas</hi> in <hi>Dio</hi> counſels young <hi>Octavian</hi> to <q rend="margQuotes">worſhip God according to his Country cuſtom, and to compel others ſo to do; but to hate and puniſh the Bringers in of ſtrange Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligions, becauſe they who bring in new Forms of Worſhip, will alſo perſwade Men to receive other Laws, and bring in as faſt as they can new Forms of Government.</q> And therefore when the <hi>National Religion</hi> comes to be queſtion'd, <hi>diſputed,</hi> and <hi>decryed,</hi> 'tis high time for the <hi>Supreme Magiſtrate</hi> to take heed that <hi>Popular Tumults</hi> and Diſturbances do not <hi>ſit hard upon the Commonwealth;</hi> for <hi>Schiſmaticks</hi> are the <hi>Stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dard-Bearers</hi> of <hi>Sedition,</hi> and the common Barretors of Mankind; <hi>Traytors in Maſqu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rade;</hi> and if <hi>their Power</hi> were anſwerable to <hi>their Spirits,</hi> they would command <hi>Fire from Heaven to burn us all up</hi> in an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:101319:15"/>
            <p>And yet to <hi>our ſhame</hi> be it ſpoken, we <hi>Engliſh-Men never know when we are well,</hi> and are juſtly reproach'd by a Proverb for being <hi>given to change;</hi> our Garbs and our Forms of Religion muſt be of the <hi>new Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>del, Cut or Faſhion:</hi> many quarrel at the <hi>Principles</hi> of that eſtabliſhed by Law, and more deſpiſe the <hi>pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of it.</hi> God has made us the <hi>Envy,</hi> and we live as if we meant to make our ſelves the <hi>Scorn of the World.</hi> Our Laws are good and many, and we live as if we had <hi>none:</hi> Our Religion is firmly eſtabliſhed by them, and we <hi>laugh it</hi> out of countenance; and the <hi>Liberty of Conſcience</hi> which we are ſo ready to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend for, is deſign'd for nothing but a <hi>Cloak of Malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I would to God it were not told in <hi>Gath,</hi> nor pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh'd <hi>in the ſtreets of Aſcalon.</hi> Are you grown ſick of your Religion and Loyalty, and with an <hi>Inconſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy natural to Iſlanders,</hi> do you affect a <hi>change</hi> for the worſe? if not, why do you <hi>meddle with them that are given to it,</hi> and why do you <hi>eſpouſe their Cauſe</hi> as if it were the <hi>darling of your own Hearts?</hi> or why will you run along with them into <hi>real</hi> and <hi>preſent,</hi> to avoid <hi>poſſible, future and imaginary miſcheifs?</hi> Would you change a <hi>Catholick Church</hi> into a ſarm of <hi>Schiſmatical Conventicles,</hi> a Flouriſhing <hi>Kingdom</hi> into a <hi>Fading Commonwealth, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity</hi> into <hi>Confuſion,</hi> the Antient <hi>Fundamental Laws</hi> of the Land into thoſe <hi>Bloudy</hi> ones which the <hi>Arbitrary Sword</hi> ſhall give you? a <hi>long and laſting peace</hi> into a more <hi>laſting War?</hi> Fulneſs into Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, <hi>Wives</hi> into <hi>Widdows, Children</hi> to Orphans, bring your ſelves into your Graves, and leave the Engliſh Nation behind you, a <hi>hiſſing and reproach</hi> to all that are round about us?</p>
            <p>Will no <hi>Charters</hi> pleaſe the <hi>Body Politick,</hi> but ſuch
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:101319:15" rendition="simple:additions"/> as may inable them <hi>to Sin with</hi> an <hi>high hand againſt the Father of our Country,</hi> from whoſe bounty they derive all their Freedoms and Priviledges? for <hi>all Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porations</hi> are the <hi>Creatures of the Crown,</hi> and when their high Stomachs will not be ſatisfied, unleſs they may <hi>devour their Makers Prerogative,</hi> they need a <hi>Charter of Pardon</hi> in ſtead of that <hi>of Freedom.</hi> Alas, that <hi>Golden Liberty</hi> which you have been vainly taught to hope for by ſome <hi>buſie Incendiaries</hi> who are now under the laſh of the Law, you would have found (as the juſt reward of your eaſie credulity) to have been nothing elſe but the <hi>Iron Fetters</hi> of the moſt <hi>Arbitrary Slaves in the World</hi> under the <hi>worſt of Alge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rines, your own fellow Subjects,</hi> the gilded <hi>Antidote</hi> which theſe State-Mountebanks offer'd you, would have prov'd a <hi>deadly poyſon;</hi> and it concerns you as much as your happineſs comes to, to take great heed, leſt by <hi>bogling at the ſhadow of Popery,</hi> plac'd only in your own deceitful imaginations, you <hi>open the door</hi> before you are aware <hi>to let in the Subſtance.</hi> He that would ſee what <hi>will be,</hi> let him ſeriouſly conſider what hath been; let him ſum up the <hi>Total Account of the profit</hi> of all that <hi>Bloud and Treaſure</hi> which was ſpent in our late <hi>unhappy Wars,</hi> for promoting the <hi>Good old Cauſe (Religion and Property</hi> the ordinary <hi>Common Places</hi> upon which Rebels declaim) and ſatisfie himſelf that there are the <hi>ſame Deſires, Humours and Intereſts</hi> drove on in this age that were in the former, and much <hi>more furiouſly</hi> now than then, by hands and mouths as like to thoſe in <hi>Forty Eight</hi> as one Egge can be to another. The grand deſign of our late <hi>ſawcy Clama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Petitioners,</hi> was the putting of the Government all <hi>out of Order,</hi> and making ſo many <hi>gaps and diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> in the <hi>Publick Fences</hi> of the Kingdom, that any
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:101319:16"/> 
               <hi>ſeditious Perſon</hi> might <hi>leap over them,</hi> or <hi>break through</hi> them at pleaſure. You had been fill'd ere this with your own deſires, <hi>if God and the King</hi> had not been <hi>merciful</hi> to you beyond your deſerts, and whatſoever you then vainly dream'd of, when you are once per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly awake, you will find <hi>ten Rebels in Maſquerade</hi> for <hi>one Romaniſt in Maſquerade,</hi> or elſe there would never have been ſo many <hi>Mechanical and Female Politicians,</hi> ſo many <hi>Blew and White Aprons</hi> (for the <hi>former</hi> are influenc'd by the later) to inform and <hi>adviſe the King</hi> and his Privy Council when <hi>to call Parliaments,</hi> and <hi>how to govern</hi> us: How can you betray <hi>greater ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude</hi> to God and the King for the <hi>peace and plenty</hi> you now do, and have ſo long jnjoy'd, than by <hi>anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipating future evils, and prejudging future providence,</hi> and for preventing <hi>imaginary</hi> miſchiefs running head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long into <hi>real</hi> ones? They fright the common people out of their <hi>Wits and Duty</hi> together, by fly-blowing their Heads with the buzzing of Plots and Deſigns in the <hi>Air</hi> againſt their Lives and Liberties, by which 'tis to be fear'd they deſign to teach them at laſt to <hi>pinion their own Happineſs,</hi> and to bring our Gracious Sovereign (whom God long preſerve) to the ſame <hi>fatal Scaffold</hi> that they did King <hi>Charles</hi> the Martyr, which no good Man can think of without the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt abhorrence imaginable. Theſe <hi>Inteſtine Incendia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> are ſet on underhand by the <hi>Court of Rome,</hi> and perhaps by <hi>another Court too,</hi> both whoſe <hi>Intereſts</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend on <hi>our Diviſions and Diſtractions,</hi> to diſperſe and foment Jealouſies between the King and the Country, by beſpattering him with a deſign of <hi>Introducing Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery and Arbitrary Government,</hi> and branding Men of more <hi>Sobriety, Juſtice and Charity,</hi> of much <hi>better Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples</hi> than themſelves, with Nicknames not fit to be
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:101319:16" rendition="simple:additions"/> mentioned here, and endeavouring <hi>to run down</hi> the <hi>beſt Men and Counſellors</hi> with <hi>Noiſe and Tumult,</hi> beyond all ſhame and reaſon, as they attempted to do ſome of our <hi>Noble Countrymen,</hi> who are the <hi>Glory of the North,</hi> and their <hi>Reputation the more Glorious</hi> after ſuch a <hi>Reſurrection</hi> as God and the King have given it. Things were lately come to that paſs, that he who was not <hi>factiouſly bent</hi> againſt his <hi>Majeſties Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive</hi> and the <hi>Churches Patrimony,</hi> and would not be ſuch a <hi>thorow-pac'd Proteſtant</hi> as not only to <hi>forſake and oppoſe Rome,</hi> but alſo to <hi>take his Freedom at Amſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,</hi> was ſtigmatiz'd as a <hi>dangerous perſon</hi> who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd the <hi>Slavery of Engliſh-men,</hi> and the Ruine and <hi>Extirpation of the True Proteſtant Religion.</hi> Take heed to your ſelves whilſt you may, before your Happineſs be fled too far <hi>out of diſtance</hi> to be retriev'd; <hi>Meddle not with them who do not fear God and the King, fear not their fear, be not afraid without a cauſe, but let the</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſai. 8. 12.</note> 
               <hi>Lord be your fear,</hi> leſt you involve your ſelves and others in the ſame Miſchiefs which <hi>Solomon</hi> foretels will infallibly light upon the Heads of them who <hi>are given to change,</hi> and of the <hi>Medlers</hi> too, which never were nor will be good for any thing till they are <hi>rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten;</hi> which brings me in the laſt place to the</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Proper Suggeſtion</hi> upon which his <hi>Prohibition</hi> is grounded, or the reaſon of this reſtraint laid upon his Son, drawn from the <hi>Changers and Medlers doom,</hi> for <hi>their calamity ſhall riſe ſuddenly, and who knows the ruine of them</hi> both? <hi>&amp; detrahentis &amp; ei feventis eorum de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractiones libenter audiendo,</hi> of him who robs the King of the Honour due to him, and of him who lends an itching ear to the diſloyal Detractor; for the <hi>Receiver is as bad as the Thief,</hi> and he who does not apprehend and diſcover him whom he finds robbing the King of
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:101319:17"/> 
               <hi>his Good Name</hi> and of his <hi>Subjects Hearts</hi> ſhall fare no better than he. When <hi>God and the King</hi> exert their <hi>Power,</hi> their <hi>Enemies ruine</hi> will be <hi>certain,</hi> whether they be <hi>Changers or Medlers,</hi> which is the firſt aggra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of their Judgment, drawn</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>A Certitudine;</hi> doubt it not, their Calamity <hi>ſhall riſe,</hi> and they who would not in time <hi>fear,</hi> ſhall then infallibly <hi>feel the juſt effects of their diſpleaſure. Be not deceiv'd, God is not mock'd, for whatſoever a Man</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 6. 7.</note> 
               <hi>ſows, that ſhall he alſo reap; for he is no reſpecter of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, but his Judgments are true and righteous altogether,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 19. 1.</note> ſo that it muſt needs be a <hi>fearful and fatal thing</hi> for a <hi>Traytor</hi> to <hi>fall into the hands of the living God, who hates Rebellion</hi> as the Sin of <hi>Witchcraft,</hi> and will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge it accordingly. No Policy, Plot, or Strength of any created thing ſhall be able to reſcue or reprieve them, when once his Vengeance hath appointed their execution, all their <hi>Slights</hi> and <hi>Tricks</hi> ſhall fail them at a <hi>dead</hi> lift; an <hi>Ignoramus Jury</hi> cannot ſerve their turns, for the ſentence of this <hi>great Judge</hi> is irrevoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, they <hi>ſhall ſoon be cut off as the graſs, and wither</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 37. 2.</note> 
               <hi>as the green herb.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Authority of <hi>God and the King</hi> muſt at any rate be <hi>redeem'd from contempt</hi> by the <hi>due execution</hi> of the Laws of both againſt obſtinate Offenders, and <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corrigible Villains,</hi> which is the <hi>Reputation and Life of the Government;</hi> and therefore <hi>Kings</hi> do not only participate of <hi>Gods Power and Patience,</hi> but muſt alſo imitate him in <hi>his Juſtice,</hi> and his <hi>manner of proceeding</hi> againſt obſtinate Rebels. Whatſoever is <hi>neceſſary,</hi> is alſo <hi>juſt,</hi> and that <hi>muſt be done</hi> which <hi>cannot be avoided.</hi> Without <hi>Government</hi> there would be no Communities of Men, and without <hi>Coercive Power</hi> there would be no Government; and as it is (not <hi>Perſecution,</hi> but)
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:101319:17" rendition="simple:additions"/> an <hi>Act of Mercy</hi> to cut off a <hi>Gangreen'd Arm</hi> from the <hi>Body Natural</hi> to preſerve the Man from periſhing; ſo is it no leſs to the <hi>Body Politick</hi> to cut off thoſe <hi>corrupt Members of the Commonwealth,</hi> which hinder the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom from flouriſhing, &amp; to prevent thoſe growing Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefs of which the <hi>Ringleaders of Rebellion</hi> are ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious to be the Authors, by <hi>ſmiting</hi> thoſe with the <hi>Sword of Juſtice,</hi> who ſmote the King and their fellow Subjects with the Fiſt of Violence. 'Tis <hi>Power</hi> that begets <hi>Fear,</hi> and <hi>Fear</hi> that <hi>makes Gods,</hi> and Rules the World; and accordingly the <hi>Pulſe of the Government</hi> beats <hi>high</hi> or <hi>low</hi> with that of the <hi>Supreme Magiſtrate,</hi> whoſe remiſneſs and <hi>connivance</hi> does prognoſtick the <hi>decay</hi> of an unſetled Government. <hi>Toleration,</hi> as harm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs and reaſonable a thing as it now ſeems, was once thought <hi>intolerable</hi> by them who now earneſtly plead for it, and will be found, if ever tryed, (as I hope it never will) to be the <hi>cauſe</hi> of many <hi>more Evils</hi> than we can eaſily foreſee, and will render the Diſeaſes and Diſtempers of the <hi>State</hi> as well as of the <hi>Church</hi> more ſtrong and <hi>powerful</hi> than any <hi>Remedies;</hi> and that <hi>King</hi> who will make <hi>his Enemies</hi> believe that he is <hi>afraid of danger</hi> in the diſcharge of his Truſt, ſhall <hi>never live without it.</hi> 'Tis better to venture ſome <hi>trouble at hand,</hi> and run the hazard of <hi>Legal Executions,</hi> than to fall under <hi>certain ruine,</hi> though ſomewhat <hi>farther diſtant.</hi> The <hi>Crowd</hi> is rather to be <hi>awed</hi> than <hi>reaſon'd with</hi> by Lawyers, it being <hi>Fear</hi> and not <hi>Love</hi> or <hi>Judgment</hi> which is their proper Paſſion: for though none are <hi>ſo bold and inſolent in their Juncto's and Cabals</hi> as they, yet none ſo <hi>faint-hearted and fearful apart.</hi> 'Twere well if <hi>Love could,</hi> but 'tis neceſſary that <hi>Fear ſhould Rule the World;</hi> and therefore 'tis <hi>ſafer</hi> to work upon them by a <hi>Power</hi> which may <hi>cure</hi> the one, than by any <hi>advantage</hi> that
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:101319:18"/> may excite the other, which they will perverſly im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute to <hi>unavoidable good Nature, Fear, Overſight,</hi> or <hi>Weakneſs;</hi> and if any of them ſeem converted by it, and are wrought over into a better mind, or put <hi>by Preferment</hi> into an <hi>hot fit of Loyalty,</hi> they will <hi>cool on a ſuddain,</hi> and prove like <hi>Witches</hi> able to <hi>do hurt,</hi> but <hi>no good</hi> at all to the Government, to <hi>raiſe the Devil</hi> of <hi>Diſcontent and Rebellion,</hi> but not to <hi>lay it;</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as if the <hi>Prince puniſh them</hi> by the ſeverity of the Law, he will <hi>oblige them</hi> or <hi>others</hi> to the obſervance of it ever after; nor will they <hi>love him</hi> for <hi>his Clemency,</hi> till he have firſt taught them <hi>to fear him</hi> for his <hi>Juſtice</hi> and Reſolution.</p>
            <p>'Tis impoſſible ever to <hi>oblige them,</hi> for they will make <hi>one Conceſſion</hi> only the Foundation of <hi>another Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt;</hi> and having uſed themſelves to deſire more than <hi>in duty becomes</hi> them, they will never think themſelves <hi>ſafe</hi> without the <hi>Sword and Scepter,</hi> as well as the <hi>Cro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſier and Miter</hi> in their Hands. It will but <hi>elevate</hi> them in their Hopes, and make them more inſolent in their Demands. Having offended the King, they will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver think themſelves <hi>ſafe</hi> till they are <hi>above his reach,</hi> and have either ſo <hi>diſarm'd him,</hi> or <hi>arm'd themſelves</hi> as not <hi>to fear him:</hi> And for as much as it hath been always found by experience that they <hi>who leaſt conſider danger</hi> in the <hi>doing their Duty fare beſt ſtill,</hi> therefore does it concern the <hi>King,</hi> and all who are put in Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority under him, <hi>to craſh this Cockatrice in the Egge</hi> as ſoon as they diſcover it. <hi>Serò Medicina paratur cum mala per long as conval<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>êre moras. Bleſſed are they that</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 106. 3.</note> 
               <hi>keep Judgment, and he that does Righteouſneſs at all times. Fiat Juſtitia ruat Coelum,</hi> is as good a <hi>Maxim</hi> in times of <hi>Peace</hi> as <hi>War;</hi> and they who <hi>do their Duty</hi> without <hi>diſputing the ſucceſs,</hi> ſhall never anſwer for
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:101319:18" rendition="simple:additions"/> thoſe <hi>accidental Effects</hi> which are contingent to their <hi>Orderly Proceedings. You ſhall not be afraid of the face</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 1. 17.</note> 
               <hi>of Man, for the Judgment is Gods,</hi> (ſays <hi>Moſes</hi>) and you are the <hi>Miniſters of God</hi> to the People <hi>for good,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 1. 14.</note> and <hi>Revengers to execute wrath upon them that do evil,</hi> ſays St. <hi>Paul,</hi> for they <hi>who reſiſt ſhall receive to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Damnation,</hi> as ſure as there is a God in Heaven; and <hi>their Calamity ſhall riſe ſuddenly,</hi> if <hi>Solomon</hi> ſay true, which is the ſecond Aggravation of their Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, drawn</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>A Celeritate:</hi> Their <hi>fall</hi> ſhall be <hi>ſudden</hi> and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expected; <hi>Their Deſtruction ſhall come as a Whirlwind, as a thing which they never looked for;</hi> They <hi>ſhall be confounded and ſore vexed, they ſhall be turned back and</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 6. 10.</note> 
               <hi>put to ſhame ſuddenly.</hi> They ſhall, like the <hi>Old World,</hi> be <hi>waſhed away in an inſtant,</hi> and conſumed like <hi>Sodom</hi> when they never dream'd on't: <hi>Before the Pots can feel the Thorns, he ſhall take them away as with a Whirl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wind,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 58. 9.</note> both <hi>living and in his anger,</hi> God will <hi>ſend forth his Warriers, and deſtroy thoſe Traytors,</hi> and <hi>they ſhall deſcend alive into Hell,</hi> whoſe Judgment does alſo ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit of a third Aggravation, drawn</p>
            <p n="3">3ly, From <hi>the ſtrangeneſs of it.</hi> 'Tis a <hi>Nemo ſcit,</hi> ſays <hi>Solomon, Who knows their ruine,</hi> or the <hi>manner</hi> of it? <hi>Is not Deſtruction to the Wicked, and a ſtrange</hi>
               <note place="margin">Job 31. 3.</note> 
               <hi>Puniſhment to the Workers of Iniquity?</hi> Traytors ſhall die an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ntimely, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nnatural,</hi> and <hi>Accurſed Death.</hi> If they would have believed <hi>Moſes,</hi> they would alſo have believed <hi>Solomon,</hi> for he told them long before that Rebels ſhould not die the common death of all Men, but periſh by a more dreadful and remarkable Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. If <hi>Corah, Dathan</hi> and <hi>Abiram</hi> enter into a <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant</hi> with Men as wicked as themſelves, <hi>to mutiny</hi>
               <note place="margin">Numb. 16. 32, 33</note> 
               <hi>againſt Moſes and Aaron,</hi> the <hi>thirſty Earth ſhall open
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:101319:19"/> her mouth and ſwallow them, and all the Men and Goods which appertain unto them ſhall periſh.</hi> If <hi>Abſalom ſteal away the Hearts of the People</hi> from his and their lawful Sovereign, the <hi>Officious Oak</hi> ſhall <hi>take him off</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 18. 9, 14.</note> 
               <hi>from his Mule</hi> by his rebellious Head, and hang him up between Heaven and Earth, as unworthy of ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: Rather than the Traytor ſhall eſcape, it ſhall play the part of <hi>Gallows, Halter</hi> and <hi>Hang man,</hi> and <hi>Joab</hi> ſhall be ſent for <hi>to thruſt three Darts through his falſe Heart,</hi> to let out that corrupt Blood at a treble Orifice, which had been ſtain'd with <hi>Diſobedience to his Parent, Treaſon to his Prince,</hi> and <hi>Hypocriſie to his God.</hi> If <hi>Sheba,</hi> or ſuch another <hi>Man of Belial, blow the Trumpet of Rebellion againſt David,</hi> the <hi>People ſhall cut</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 20. 22.</note> 
               <hi>off his Head, and throw it out to Joab. Had Zimri Peace who ſlew his Maſter?</hi> He <hi>Fir'd the Kings Houſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 King. 16. 18.</note> but himſelf was alſo <hi>burn'd in it.</hi> Their <hi>own Hands</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 King. 9. 31</note> ſhall become their <hi>Executioners,</hi> their <hi>own Blaſphemous Tongues ſhall make them to fall,</hi> their own Complices and Confederates ſhall riſe up in Judgment againſt them, and their <hi>ruine ſhall</hi> be very <hi>ſtrange,</hi> both as to the <hi>manner,</hi> and alſo</p>
            <p n="4">4ly, As to the <hi>extent of it,</hi> for one Puniſhment ſhall tread upon the heels of another, and where <hi>Old</hi> go off, <hi>New Scenes of Miſeries</hi> ſhall take <hi>their turns.</hi> They ſhall paſs from one Torment to another, from <hi>Temporal</hi> to <hi>Eternal,</hi> and ſo go down <hi>by ſteps to Hell. I counſel thee</hi> (ſays our Wiſe Man) <hi>to keep the Kings</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccl. 8. 3, 4.</note> 
               <hi>Commandment, and that in regard of the Oath of God. Be not haſty to go out of his ſight, ſtand not in an evil thing, for he doth whatſoever pleaſeth him.</hi> You may as well allow <hi>Children</hi> to riſe up againſt their <hi>Parents, Servants</hi> againſt their <hi>Maſters,</hi> and <hi>Common Souldiers</hi> againſt their <hi>Commander's,</hi> as <hi>Subjects</hi> in any caſe againſt
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:101319:19" rendition="simple:additions"/> their <hi>Sovereign,</hi> their <hi>Power</hi> being but <hi>Inferiour Bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches</hi> of that <hi>Sovereignty</hi> which is <hi>rooted in him,</hi> as the common Parent, great Maſter, and Supreme Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander of us all. <hi>Where the Word of a King is, there is Power, and who may ſay unto him, What doſt thou?</hi> Who may not, when every Tradeſman thinks it a part of his Freedom to intermeddle with the Kings proper Buſineſs; and yet they who contradict and controul him, ſhall at long running <hi>ſmart</hi> ſeverely for it, <hi>their Names</hi> ſhall be loaded with <hi>Infamy</hi> and <hi>Reproach</hi> to Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity, their <hi>Blood ſtain'd and attainted,</hi> and their <hi>Families ruin'd.</hi> Nay, if <hi>they ſpeak evil of the King,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccl. 10. 20.</note> though but in <hi>their Hearts,</hi> God, whoſe Perſon he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſents, and whoſe place he here ſupplies, hath threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned both to <hi>diſcloſe it,</hi> and to be <hi>aveng'd</hi> of him for it. Let them cover their Crimes with all the ſubtilty they can from Men, there is a <hi>God above all the Tricks</hi> both of <hi>Changers and Medlers,</hi> who will find them and their rebellious Deſigns out at laſt, and diſcover their Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanies to Men and Angels; and notwithſtanding all <hi>the Snow-water with which they have waſh'd their Hands,</hi> to make them look like <hi>Loyal Subjects and good Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants,</hi> he will for the filthineſs of their rebellious Hearts <hi>plunge them into the bottomleſs Pit, out of which there is no redemption: His Anger ſhall ſmoak againſt them in this Life,</hi> and they ſhall <hi>ſuffer the Vengeance of Eternal Fire</hi> in that to come; after a <hi>Temporal</hi> Death, an <hi>Eternal</hi> Damnation.</p>
            <p>Rebels do uſually promiſe themſelves and other cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulous People, <hi>great Matters</hi> in the <hi>Golden Age of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation,</hi> if they can overcome the King; but they ſhall become <hi>Felo's de ſe,</hi> they ſhall <hi>Damn themſelves</hi> by their Projects, for God will never <hi>be Friends with them</hi> who are <hi>Enemies to the King;</hi> and except they
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:101319:20"/> 
               <hi>obey both,</hi> they ſhall be puniſh'd as if they had <hi>obey'd</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 13. 2.</note> 
               <hi>neither,</hi> and <hi>receive to themſelves Damnation.</hi> And therefore, <hi>My Son, fear God and the King,</hi> not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for fear of <hi>Temporal Puniſhment,</hi> which ſome <hi>Daring Traytors</hi> have <hi>undergone and contemn'd,</hi> and other <hi>Proſperous Rebels</hi> have avoided and eſcaped by an <hi>Act</hi> of <hi>Indempnity or Pardon,</hi> but in Obedience to the <hi>Conſtitution of God,</hi> whoſe Officer he is, and in reference to your <hi>own Eternal Salvation,</hi> which you will thereby infallibly forfeit, though you ſhould be comprehended in an Act of Oblivion, or a General Pardon.</p>
            <p>I hope I have ſaid more than enough to convince all that hear me this day of the <hi>Obligation</hi> which lies upon them to take the <hi>Wiſe Mans Advice</hi> in my Text; and that You, my very <hi>Honoured Friends,</hi> for <hi>whoſe ſake</hi> I have preſs'd it, will declare by your <hi>Exemplary Piety and Loyalty,</hi> your approbation of it.</p>
            <p>No <hi>County</hi> in all his Majeſties Dominions was ever yet Corrival with <hi>Yorkſhire</hi> for <hi>Greatneſs</hi> or <hi>Goodneſs;</hi> None have more <hi>Lords, Knights, and Gentlemen of the beſt Quality</hi> in it, of which they profer'd, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came dutiful Subjects, to raiſe <hi>King CHARLES the Martyr a Life-guard for his Royal Perſon,</hi> which in confidence of their <hi>Loyalty</hi> he <hi>graciouſly accepted,</hi> and honour'd them, by making the <hi>Prince of Wales,</hi> our preſent Gracious Sovereign, (whom God long pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve) the <hi>Captain</hi> of it. The <hi>then Loyal City of York</hi> receiv'd his Sacred Majeſty, when he was driven out of <hi>This</hi> by Seditious Tumults, and thither did he aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble his <hi>great Council.</hi> And if I had not <hi>treſpaſs'd</hi> already too much upon your <hi>Patience,</hi> or did in the leaſt ſuſpect that you <hi>needed</hi> more Motives to Loyalty
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:101319:20" rendition="simple:additions"/> than thoſe which <hi>this Text,</hi> and my Diſcourſe on it, hath already afforded you, I ſhould deſcend to ſome <hi>Local and Perſonal Obligations</hi> which lie more upon You, than other Men, to engage you to it. I could eaſily reckon up many <hi>Towns</hi> and <hi>Fields</hi> in your <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> beſides your <hi>Metropolis,</hi> in which your <hi>Loyal An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors</hi> did ſacrifice their Lives for his Service; eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially at the fatal Battel of <hi>Marſton-More:</hi> Nor can I forget thoſe who died <hi>Martyrs for their Loyalty on Tower-Hill,</hi> whoſe Loyal Blood runs ſtill in the Veins of their Children. I dare not be ſo uncharitable as ſuſpect that you <hi>Inherit the Eſtates</hi> of your Loyal An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors without <hi>their Virtues;</hi> and I hope you will convince the World that <hi>Yorkſhire</hi> Men are born in too free an Air to have their Spirits tainted with Schiſm or Sedition, which are the moſt <hi>pernicious Peſts and Plagues</hi> of any County where they reign, <hi>for which things ſake the Wrath of God comes upon the Children of Diſobedience.</hi> There never was ſuch a <hi>Superfoetation of thoſe Brats</hi> in any Age as in this, (to our ſhame be it ſpoken) wherein Men lately acted, as if they deſign'd to <hi>put Loyalty out of Countenance,</hi> and <hi>ridicule</hi> it out of the Kindgdom. If any of You were unhappily ſeduced into ſuch <hi>Diſloyal Conſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies,</hi> I hope you have ask'd <hi>God and the King Pardon</hi> for it, and that you will always do as much as in you lies to ſhew your ſelves <hi>thankful</hi> for their Mercies. I know how ill it becomes me to give my Betters that, which I need too much my ſelf; and therefore I ſhall refer you to the Counſel of a <hi>Great Country-man of your own,</hi> who is now plac'd above cenſure, and <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing dead does yet ſpeak,</hi> Sir <hi>John Packering Lord Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor of England in Queen Elizabeth's Reign,</hi> that which he then gave the Parliament in that Glorious
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:101319:21"/> Age of Reformation, I hope I may without offence to all good Men repeat to you, whoſe Advice was this:</p>
            <p>
               <q rend="margQuotes">Liſten not to the weariſom Sollicitations of the <hi>new-fangled Refiners,</hi> commonly called <hi>Puritans,</hi> who diſturb the good Repoſe of Church and Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, whom you will find <hi>more dangerous</hi> than the <hi>Jeſuites</hi> in poyſoning the Hearts of good Subjects, under <hi>Pretence of Conſcience</hi> to withdraw them from their Obedience; with whom though in other Points they <hi>pretend to differ,</hi> yet do they <hi>joyn</hi> and concur with them in ſeparation of themſelves from the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of their fellow Subjects,</hi> and in <hi>abaſing the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Authority</hi> and Majeſty of their Prince, which 'tis the <hi>Common Intereſt and Advantage</hi> of Mankind to uphold and honour.</q>
            </p>
            <p>I am ſure 'tis both <hi>our Duty and Intereſt</hi> to hazard our Lives in his Majeſties Service againſt all Rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Oppoſers whatſoever, before they be tamely ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from us, (as we know whoſe were) by Uſurping Inſolent Traytors. We ſhall have <hi>liv'd too long,</hi> if we <hi>out-live the Loyalty of Engliſh-men,</hi> which is the <hi>Priviledge and Glory of free-born Subjects,</hi> and ſhould be the <hi>Security</hi> of our Gracious Sovereign in his <hi>Juſt Prerogatives.</hi> Nature teaches all Men to guard the <hi>Head,</hi> even with the hazard of the other Members; and can we ſo eaſily forget how ſoundly we were <hi>fleec'd by <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurping Tyrants,</hi> that we will twice in an Age liſten to thoſe <hi>Country-men of Publick Spirits,</hi> (as they did then, and do ſtill call themſelves) who ſhall tempt us to refuſe what is <hi>juſt</hi> and <hi>neceſſary</hi> for the <hi>ſupport of the Government</hi> under a lawful Prince, who
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:101319:21" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
               <hi>requires leſs</hi> than every <hi>good Subject</hi> is cordially wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to contribute upon ſuch Honourable Emergen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies? They who will not part with <hi>half ſo much</hi> for a <hi>Common Good</hi> as they will prodigally ſpend up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a <hi>Boon Companion, or a Common Miſs,</hi> do neither fear God nor the King as they ought to do.</p>
            <p>If there be any thing <hi>in Fame</hi> worthy of your Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition, True <hi>Piety and Loyalty</hi> (the <hi>Methods preſcrib'd you in my Text</hi>) are the <hi>ſhorteſt</hi> and <hi>ſureſt way</hi> to it: for Poſterity will reflect upon <hi>your Actions</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>Prejudice or Intereſt,</hi> and <hi>Canonize</hi> the <hi>beſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians and Subjects</hi> for the <hi>Greateſt Men of the Age;</hi> This is the Beauty of that <hi>Image</hi> in which we were made, the <hi>faireſt Veſtment</hi> that our Souls can be adorn'd with till they are <hi>Cloath'd with Immortality;</hi> and if you wear <hi>this Livery,</hi> the King of Heaven will make you <hi>free of a better City</hi> than this, <hi>One not made with Hands, free Denizons of the New Jeruſalem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As therefore you tender the <hi>Glory of God,</hi> the <hi>Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit and Increaſe</hi> of <hi>your Religion</hi> by Law eſtabliſhed, your own <hi>Temporal</hi> and <hi>Spiritual Happineſs</hi> here, and your <hi>Eternal</hi> hereafter, <hi>withdraw your ſelves</hi> from the Society of Men of <hi>Rebellious Principles,</hi> whether they bring them from <hi>Rome</hi> or <hi>Geneva,</hi> from the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clave</hi> or a <hi>Conventicle,</hi> and be as <hi>active</hi> to maintain the King in his <hi>Juſt Rights and Royalties,</hi> as the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man or Republican Agitators</hi> have been to undermine them; and unleſs you are <hi>Sick of your Religion, Laws and Liberties,</hi> (and I pray God we prove not ſo, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond all hopes of recovery) let us all ſhew as much <hi>Zeal</hi> in defending them againſt the Kings and Gods Enemies, as they do <hi>Earneſtneſs</hi> in aſſaulting them, and him through their ſides. If not for <hi>Honour and Loyalty ſake,</hi> as we deſire to hear in other <hi>Nations,</hi>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:101319:22"/> and <hi>After-Ages;</hi> if not <hi>for Wrath,</hi> and fear of ruine to our ſelves and Families; yet for our <hi>Oaths and Gods ſake,</hi> for the <hi>Churches, Conſcience, Poſterity and Peace ſake,</hi> let us ſincerely practiſe <hi>Subjection to God and the King</hi> as becomes <hi>good Chriſtians and Subjects</hi> for our Bleſſed Saviours ſake, that <hi>Great Patron and Pattern of Obedience,</hi> and pray unto him that he would ſcatter all His and the Kings cruel Enemies <hi>that delight in Blood;</hi> Infatuate the Counſels of their <hi>Achitophels,</hi> and root out all thoſe <hi>Babylo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian, Antichriſtian,</hi> and <hi>Anti-Monarchical Rebels,</hi> who have decreed in their Hearts and Cabals againſt our Gracious Sovereign as the <hi>Aramites</hi> did againſt the <hi>King of Iſrael; Fight neither againſt ſmall nor</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 King. 22. 31</note> 
               <hi>great, but only againſt</hi> the <hi>King of Great Britain;</hi> and ſaid of our <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> the Church of <hi>England,</hi> Pull <hi>down the Fences of it, raſe it even to the Ground,</hi> that the <hi>Confuſions of Babel</hi> may be heard no more among us, but we become <hi>like Jeruſalem a City at <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in it ſelf.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let this thine Almightly Work, O King of Kings, <hi>and only Ruler of Princes,</hi> appear unto thy Servants, and the Glory of it to their Children; So <hi>we thy People will give thee thanks for ever, and will be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways ſhewing forth thy Praiſe from Generation to Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration,</hi> through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord.</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:101319:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
